Guide to the John Ericsson Collection 1831-1893 (bulk 1862-1888) MS 439.16
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
John Ericsson Collection
1831-1893 (bulk 1862-1888)
MS 439.16
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
9.0 Linear feet (21 boxes, 2 volumes)
The collection includes correspondence and other materials detailing Ericsson's design and testing of iron-clad and torpedo-armed ships for the US and other navies, including Monitor and Destroyer, as well as his writings on other areas of interest.
Provenance
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by the Naval History Society in 1925.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)[ Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.]
Biographical Note
Born in Sweden in 1803, Ericsson emigrated first to England (1826) and then to the United States (1839). Having shown early promise as an engineer, and holding numerous patents for steam-powered engines, he designed the first screw-driven steamship to cross the Atlantic ( Robert F. Stockton, 1839) and the first propeller-driven steam warship for the US Navy (USS Princeton, 1842). In 1861 he contracted with the Navy to build in 100 days an ironclad warship, Monitor, which successfully fought the Confederate ironclad Virginia (originally Merrimack) at Hampton Roads on March 9, 1862, before sinking off Cape Hatteras later that year. After the Civil War, he pursued his interests in torpedo-armed vessels, and in a variety of scientific and engineering subjects, including solar energy. He died in New York in 1889 and was interred in Sweden in 1890.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes original correspondence to and copies from John Ericsson (the latter predominantly in the hand of his secretary, Samuel W. Taylor, and a few autograph) as well as telegrams, invoices, receipts, writings, clippings, articles, an account book, and a volume listing his articles on torpedo warfare. The materials were a gift in 1912 to the Naval History Society from Ericsson's biographer William Conant Church, and the correspondence is annotated and underlined throughout in various colors, perhaps by him as part of his research for "The Life of John Ericsson" (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1890). Undated materials appear to have been from Church's research and papers, and include separated and unidentified documents. The materials are mostly in English, with some in Swedish and German.
The collection documents many aspects of Ericsson's engineering interests and projects: the building and testing of ironclad warships to his specifications for the United States (USS Monitor, 1862) and other governments (Peru: May 1862; Greece: January 1869; Spain: May 1869; China: October 1880, spring 1883); the costs of construction through his extensive contact with Delamater and other ironworks and foundries as well as negotiations with Congress (1864-1865); applications and renewals of patents (1830s, 1840s, December 1864, July 1866); experiments with solar energy (1868, July 1872); design and testing of torpedo warships, including detailed expenses for Destroyer (January 1873, September 1874, April 1875, 1878-1882, January 1889) and reports on its trials (October 1883); as well as various complete lists of ironclads built to Ericsson's specifications (May 1866, December 1867, July 1877).
Highlights of the collection include copies of Ericsson's January 20, 1862, letter to Assistant Secretary of the Navy Gustavus Vasa Fox (see Series 17), proposing the name Monitor for his ironclad vessel; and his January 30, 1873, letter to President Ulysses S. Grant explaining that the torpedo systems currently in use are inadequate for the country's defense.
The Ericsson Collection forms Series 16 of the Naval History Society Collection, comprising 53 individual collections named for famous naval figures and ships, as well as the records of the Naval History Society itself, and donated to the New-York Historical Society by the Naval History Society in 1925.
An extensive collection of Ericsson's papers is housed at the
Library of Congress
.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
A chronological inventory of the papers of John Ericsson (from 1831 to July 1865 only) in the Naval History Society's collection was prepared in 1984 and is available in the repository.
The John Ericsson papers owned by the American Swedish Historical Foundation are available on microfilm.
The New-York Historical Society's Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection includes three autograph letters of John Ericsson's.
Delamater Iron Works; Delamater, Cornelius H., 1821-1889; Ericsson, John, 1803-1889; Fox, Gustavus Vasa, 1821-1883; Griswold, John A., 1822-1872;; Clippings; Contracts; Destroyer (Ship); Drawings; Invoices; Letters; Monitor (Ironclad); Patent applications; Shipbuilding; Ships, Iron and steel; Telegrams; United States - History -Civil War; United States. Navy - - History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 - Naval Operations
  - Correspondence, 1831-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1862 January 3 - February 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1862 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1862 April 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1862 April 15-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1862 May 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1862 May 15-31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1862 June - July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1862 August - September (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1862 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1862 November (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1863 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1863 February (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1863 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1863 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1863 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1863 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1863 July - August (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1863 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1863 October (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1863 November - December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 January (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 February 1 - 18 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 February 19 - 29 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1864 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1864 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 June 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 June 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1864 August 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1864 August 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1864 September (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1864 October 1-18 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 October 19-31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1864 November (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1864 December (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1865 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1865 March (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1865 April (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1865 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865 June - July (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1865 August (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1865 September (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1865 October (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 November (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1865 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Undated [1831-1865] (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1866 January (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1866 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1866 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1866 April (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1866 May (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1866 June (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1866 July (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1866 August (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1866 September (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1866 October (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1866 November (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1866 December (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1867 January (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1867 February (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1867 March (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1867 April (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1867 May-June (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1867 July-August (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1867 September - November (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1867 December (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1868 January (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1868 February-March (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1868 April-May (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1868 June-July (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1868 August (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868 September - October (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1868 November - December (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1869 January - February (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1869 March (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1869 April (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1869 May (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1869 June (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1869 July (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1869 August (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1869 September (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1869 October (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1869 November (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1869 December (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1870 January (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870 February - March (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1870 April (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1870 May - June (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1870 July - September (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1870 October - December (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1871 January -February (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1871 March - April (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1871 May - July (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1871 August (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1871 September - October (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1871 November - December (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1872 January - February (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1872 March - April (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1872 May - June (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1872 July - September (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1872 October- December (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1873 January (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1873 February - March (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1873 April - May (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1873 June - July (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1873 August-September (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1873 October - November (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1873 December (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1874 January - March (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1874 April (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1874 May-June (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1874 July (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1874 August (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1874 September (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1874 October 1-14 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1874 October 15-28 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1874 November - December (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1875 January - March (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1875 April - July (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1875 August - December (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1876 January (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1876 February (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1876 March (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1876 April - May (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1876 June (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1876 July - August (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1876 September - October (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1876 November - December (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1877 January - February (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1877 March - April (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1877 May (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1877 June (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1877 July (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1877 August - September (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1877 October (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1877 November - December (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1878 January - February (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1878 March (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1878 April (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1878 May (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1878 June - July (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1878 August (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1878 September (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1878 October (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1878 November (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1878 December (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1879 January (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1879 February - March (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1879 April (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1879 May (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1879 June (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1879 July (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1879 August (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1879 September - October (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1879 November (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1879 December (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1880 January - March (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1880 April (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1880 May-June (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1880 July (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1880 August (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1880 September - October (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1880 November (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1880 December (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1881 January (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1881 February (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1881 March - April (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1881 May - June (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1881 July - September (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1881 October - December (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1882 January (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1882 February (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1882 March - April (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1882 May - June (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1882 July - September (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1882 October (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1882 November (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1883 January (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1883 February (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1883 March (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1883 April (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1883 May (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1883 June (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1883 July (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1883 August (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1883 September (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1883 October (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1883 November (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1883 December (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Undated [1883] (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1884 January (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1884 February (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1884 March - April (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1884 May - June (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1884 July - August (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1884 September - October (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1884 November - December (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1885 January (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1885 February (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1885 March - April (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1885 May - July (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1885 August (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1885 September (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1885 October (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1885 November (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1885 December (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1886 January - February (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1886 March - April (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1886 May - June (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1886 July (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1886 August (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Essays: Diathermancy of the terrestrial atmosphere; Zenith distances at equal time before and after noon, 1886 August - September (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1886 September - October (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1886 November - December (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1887 January (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1887 February (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1887 March (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1887 April (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1887 May - June (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1887 July (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1887 August (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1887 September (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1887 October (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1887 November (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1887 December (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1888 January - February (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1888 March - April (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1888 May - July (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1888 August (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1888 September (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1888 October (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1888 December - 1889 January (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous papers, Undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers, Undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Printed material, 1844-1885, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Printed material, 1853-1887, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Letter to William C. Church, 1889 August 5 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Invitation to unveiling of Ericsson Statue, Battery Park, 1893 April 26 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Iron clads of the US Navy (2/2), 1866 May (Box OS 2, Folder 4)
  - Account book, 1864 June - 1872 (Volume 1)
  - Torpedo articles: articles published, correspondents sent to, list of important papers, list of articles relating to torpedoes, 1869-1884 (Volume 2)